Register of the Tom Killion papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Tom Killion papers
1868-1997
2017C40
Hoover Institution Archives
25 manuscript boxes, 2 card file boxes, 4 oversize boxes (14.8 linear feet)
Correspondence, writings, notes, government documents, bulletins, serial issues, printed matter, photographs, and sound recordings relating to the history of Ethiopia and Eritrea, especially to labor and nationalist movements in those countries.
Killion, Tom
Access
The collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2017.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Tom Killion was born on November 28, 1953, and was raised in Marin County, California. In 1975 he received his B.A. in history from the University of California, Santa Cruz. He went on to receive a Ph.D in African history with a dissertation on the Ethiopian/Eritrean labor movement from Stanford University in 1985. From 1987 to 1988 Killion worked as an administrator for medical programs in three refugee camps in Eastern Sudan near Showak. In March of 1988 he travelled in the liberated zone of Eritrea with the Eritrean People's Liberation Front, witnessing the battle of Afabet and reporting on it for the Los Angeles Times.
From 1990 to 1995 Killion was an Assistant Professor of African History at Bowdoin College. Between 1993 and 1994 Killion was a Fulbright Professor at Asmara University in Eritrea. He later taught courses at Stanford and from 1995 to 2001 was a guest lecturer in the Humanities Department at San Francisco State University.
In the early 1990s, Killion helped found the Eritrean Studies Association and organized the first Eritrean Studies Conference at San Francisco State University. His Historical Dictionary of Eritrea remains a notable resource in the field.
Killion is also a nationally recognized woodcut printmaker, for which he has received many awards and participated in many exhibitions, as well as the 2009 PBS-TV documentary, Craft in America: Process. He owns Quail Press, which he founded in 1977.
Scope and Content of Collection
Correspondence, dissertation and research notes, reports, flyers, pamphlets, and other printed matter relating to political, economic, cultural, and social affairs in the Horn of Africa, in general, and in Eritrea, Ethiopia, and Sudan, in particular.
Eritrea--History.; Ethiopia--History.; Labor movement--Eritrea; Labor movement--Ethiopia
- Office File, 1980-1991 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Contains business and invitation cards, and invoices.
  - Contacts and business cards, 1980s (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Copying, 1990s (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Invitation to a reception (50th anniversary of Victory Days), 1991 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Invoices and packing slip, 1983-1984 (Box-folder 1: 4)
- Correspondence, 1964-1997 (Boxes 1-2)
  Comprised of personal and organizational letters.
  - Adolff, Richard, 1982 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Africa World Press (AWP)/Red Sea Press (RSP), 1997 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - African American Labor Center, 1982 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - AMMAR, Woldeyesus, 1995-1996 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Anfray, Francis, 1994 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Auriol, Mm J., 1982 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Blane, John, 1982 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Buffier, Jean Joseph, 1982 (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - Cacqueray, Henri de, 1982 (Box-folder 1: 13)
  - Cochat, René, 1982 (Box-folder 1: 14)
  - Connell, Dan, 1996 (Box-folder 1: 15)
  - Deflandre, M. R., 1982 (Box-folder 1: 16)
  - Department of Commerce (U.S.), 1982 (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - De Marinis, Paul, 1986 (Box-folder 1: 18)
  - Eritreans for Liberation in North America (EFLNA), 1979 (Box-folder 1: 19)
  - Estifanos, 1981 (Box-folder 1: 20)
  - Ethiopian Internal Security, 1981 (Box-folder 1: 21)
  - Gebreselassie and Mesfin, 1964 (Box-folder 1: 22)
  - Gebrehiwet, Hagos, 1992 (Box-folder 1: 23)
  - Grey, Robert D., 1991 (Box-folder 1: 24)
  - Gueleh, Idris Omar, 1983 (Box-folder 1: 25)
  - Guiraud, R., 1982 (Box-folder 1: 26)
  - Habteselassie, Bereket, 1992 (Box-folder 1: 27)
  - Hendrie, Barbara, 1996 (Box-folder 1: 28)
  - Hodgin, Peter, 1995 (Box-folder 1: 29)
  - Iyob, Ruth, 1991 (Box-folder 1: 30)
  - Jackson, Kennell Jr., 1992 (Box-folder 1: 31)
  - Kane, Thomas L., 1994 (Box-folder 1: 32)
  - Lebegue, Yves, 1982 (Box-folder 1: 33)
  - Lino, James George, 1996 (Box-folder 1: 34)
  - Looram, Matthew, 1982 (Box-folder 1: 35)
  - Manspeizer, Ilyssa, 1995 (Box-folder 1: 36)
  - Marchal, Roland, undated (Box-folder 1: 37)
  - Marcus, Harold, 1991-1995 (Box-folder 1: 38)
  - McCann, Jim, 1990 (Box-folder 1: 39)
  - Pasteau, Michel, 1982 (Box-folder 1: 40)
  - Schröder, Günter, 1990 (Box-folder 1: 41)
  - Shapird, Martin, undated (Box-folder 1: 42)
  - Stanford University, 1980 (Box-folder 1: 43)
  - Stutz, Robert L., 1982 (Box-folder 1: 44)
  - Taffesse, Yohannes, 1982-1983 (Box-folder 1: 45)
  - Tamrat, Taddesse, 1981 (Box-folder 1: 46)
  - Tekle, Amare, 1992 (Box-folder 1: 47)
  - Tholomier, Robert, 1982-1983 (Box-folder 1: 48)
  - Toche, 1982 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Ullendorff, Edward, 1983 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - Verbrugge, C. V., 1982 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - Videau, Daniel, 1982 (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - Villele, Guillaume de, 1982 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - Wamba-dia-Wamba, Ernest, undated (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - Wylie, Dean, 1992 (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - Zongo, Opportune, 1992 (Box-folder 2: 8)
- Speeches and Writings, 1970-1997 (Boxes 2-6)
  Contains dissertation outlines, research notes, lecture notes, and articles.
  - African Adaptive Institution and Labor Unions, undated (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - African Studies Association (ASA) conference, Eritrea notes, 1991 (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - Articles by Tom Killion for Eritrea Profile, 1994 (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - Bibliography, 1980s-1990s, undated (Box-folder 2: 12)
  - Biographical sketches of Eritrean People's Liberation Front (EPLF) and Eritrean government leaders for Historical Dictionary of Eritrea, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 2: 13)
  - Call for papers on Eritrea for Eritrean Studies Review, 1996 (Box-folder 2: 14)
  - "Capitalization of North and South," chapter one, second draft, 1981 (Box-folder 2: 15)
  - "Class and Nation in Eritrea: Workers' Organization and the Development of Multiethnic Nationalism, 1952-1962," typed essay, undated (Box-folder 2: 16)
  - Comments on Dan Connell's "Focus" on Eritrea, draft, 1995 (Box-folder 2: 17)
  - Cultural organizations, handwritten notes, 1994 (Box-folder 2: 18)
  - Dissertation
    Scope and Contents note
    Includes typed drafts, notes, and typed chapters from Tom Killion's dissertation and his research at Asmara University.
    - Chapter 1, "Patterns of Uneven Capitalist Penetration and Working Class Formation,", 1981 (Box-folder 2: 19)
    - Chapter 1, "Patterns of Uneven Capitalist Penetration and Working Class Formation," various drafts, 1981 (Box-folder 2: 20)
    - Notes, 1981 (Box-folder 2: 21)
    - Notes on Franco-Ethiopian Railroad, 1981 (Box-folder 2: 22)
    - Research notes, 1981-1996 (Box-folder 2: 23)
    - Research proposal, first draft, 1981 (Box-folder 3: 1)
    - Research proposal, 1981 (Box-folder 3: 2)
    - Research proposal, final draft, 1981 (Box-folder 3: 3)
    - Research proposal, "Organized Labor, Nationalism and Revolution in Ethiopia and Eritrea, 1945-1975,", 1981 (Box-folder 3: 4)
    - Revision notes, 1980s (Box-folder 3: 5)
    - "Education and Nation Building,", 1993 (Box-folder 3: 6)
    - "Eritrea: Challenges of National Reconstruction,", 1994 (Box-folder 3: 7)
    - Eritrea: Early colonial period, 1980s (Box-folder 3: 8)
      Includes handwritten notes and "The Empire of Work in Eritrea 1935-1941," a typed essay.
    - "Eritrea: Heritage of War and the Challenge of National Reconstruction,", 1994 (Box-folder 3: 9)
    - Eritrea notes, 1993-1994 (Box-folder 3: 10)
    - "Eritrean Historical Studies: A Review of the Field,", 1993 (Box-folder 3: 11)
    - "Eritrean History: A Review of the Literature,", 1993-1994 (Box-folder 3: 12)
    - Eritrean Studies Newsletter [Killion, Tom, "The Eritrean Jihad and Repatriation of Refugees"], 1994 (Box-folder 3: 13)
    - "Eritrean Workers' Organization in the Colonial Period: 1890-1991,", 1993 (Box-folder 3: 14)
    - "Eritrean Workers' Organization and Early Nationalist Mobilization: 1948-1958,", 1997 (Box-folder 3: 15)
    - "Historical Interpretation of Underdevelopment Theory in Africa I: The Problem of the Formation of the West African Colonial Middle Class,", 1979 (Box-folder 3: 16)
      Tom Killion's third essay from his History 347 class during college.
    - "Historical Interpretation of Underdevelopment Theory in Africa II: The Problems of the Colonial Model of Afro-European Relations,", 1979 (Box-folder 3: 17)
      Tom Killion's fourth essay from his History 347 class during college.
    - Ideology, "Why I Joined the Eritrean People's Liberation Front," handwritten notes, 1994 (Box-folder 3: 18)
    - Interviews with Eritrean workers, 1994 (Box-folder 3: 19)
    - "Introduction to Ethiopian Labor History: Workers' Organization in the Modern Sector, 1900-1974,", 1981 (Box-folder 3: 20)
    - "Introduction: Workers' Organization and National Consciousness,", 1994 (Box-folder 3: 21)
    - Lecture, "National Union of Eritrean Workers," Asmara University, 1994 (Box-folder 3: 22)
    - Labor movement, handwritten notes, 1980s (Box-folder 3: 23)
    - Martyrdom/ideology, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 4: 1)
    - "National Service in the Eyes of Professor Tom Killion," interview in Haddas Eritrea/New Eritrea, 1994 (Box-folder 4: 2)
    - Newspaper article on Tom Killion's presentation of Eritrean labor, 1994 (Box-folder 4: 3)
    - Newspaper articles, 1989, 1992 (Box-folder 4: 4)
      Publications include The Los Angeles Times and The Ethiopian Herald.
  - Notes
    - Chronology, Ethiopia and Eritrea, 1980s-1990s, undated (Box-folder 4: 5)
    - Eritrea labor history and Ethiopia CELU history, 1970, 1994 (Box-folder 4: 6)
    - Ethiopian Studies conference, Addis Ababa, 1991 (Box-folder 4: 7)
    - Historical Dictionary of Eritrea, 1994 (Box-folder 4: 8)
    - Il Bollettino, circa 1990 (Box-folder 4: 9)
    - Marxian economics, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 4: 10)
    - Military history, Eritrea, 1990 (Box-folder 4: 11)
    - Nationalism, 1990 (Box-folder 4: 12)
    - Okbazghi Yohannes' book, 1990 (Box-folder 4: 13)
    - Useful citations, 1994 (Box-folder 4: 14)
    - Various, 1981 (Box-folder 4: 15)
    - Various, undated (Box-folder 4: 16)
    - "Popular Mobilizations in the Eritrean National Liberation Struggle," guest editor's introduction, 1995-1996 (Box-folder 4: 17)
    - "Positive Nationalism?,", 1994 (Box-folder 4: 18)
    - "Problems of Nation-Building in Independent Eritrea: Secular Nationalism and the Islamist Alternative,", undated (Box-folder 4: 19)
    - Proposed research project, "A History of the Eritrean General Strike of 1958," typed essay draft, 1993 (Box-folder 4: 20)
    - Questionnaire, history of the armed struggle, fighters' experiences, 1994 (Box-folder 4: 21)
    - "Railroad Workers and the Ethiopian Imperial State: The Politics of Workers' Organization on the Franco-Ethiopian Railroad, 1919-1959," typed revised essay, 1992 (Box-folder 4: 22)
    - "Refugees and Environmental Change on the Sudano-Ethiopian Frontier: The History of the Wad el-Hilean Refugee Camp, 1967-1987," typed revised essay, 1992 (Box-folder 4: 23)
  - Research notes
    Includes handwritten notes and essays written by Tom Killion featuring editorial notes. Most essays are dated during Killion's college years.
    - 1980s-1990s (Box-folder 4: 24)
    - Afar, 1991 (Box-folder 4: 25)
    - "An Introduction to the Economic History of Ethiopia,", undated (Box-folder 4: 26)
    - Eritrea Center for International Programs, Michigan State University, 1989 (Box-folder 4: 27)
    - Isaias Afewerki, 1987-1993 (Box-folder 4: 28)
    - Labor, 1970-1980 (Box-folder 5: 1)
    - Newspapers in Eritrea, first list, 1994 (Box-folder 5: 2)
    - Workers in African literature, 1980s (Box-folder 5: 3)
    - "Review of Eritrean Historical Studies in the Context of National Independence,", 1993 (Box-folder 5: 4)
    - "Teenage Soldiers in the Eritrean War," draft, 1990 (Box-folder 5: 5)
    - "The Development of National Political Consciousness in Eritrean Christian Community, 1949-1975,", 1989 (Box-folder 5: 6)
    - "The Emergence of Eritrean Nationalism in the 1940s,", 1979 (Box-folder 5: 7)
    - "The Eritrean Economy in Historical Perspective,", 1993-1994 (Box-folder 5: 8)
    - "The Eritrean Labor Movement: A Brief History,", 1996 (Box-folder 5: 9)
    - "The Formation and Politics of Tigriyan Nationalism in Eritrea During the British Period of Administration: 1941-1950,", 1979 (Box-folder 5: 10)
    - "The Influence of Christianity in the 'Mau Mau' Independence Movement in Kenya, 1952-1956,", 1978 (Box-folder 5: 11)
    - "The Islamic Model and Wolof Adaptation to the Colonial Situation: The Development of the Mourides,", 1979 (Box-folder 5: 12)
    - "The Making of Modern Eritrea: From Regional Identity to National Consciousness,", 1993 (Box-folder 5: 13)
    - "The Outbreak of the First World War and the Internal Dimensions of Imperialism,", 1980 (Box-folder 5: 14)
    - Thesis outline, "Workers' Organization and the State in Ethiopia and Eritrea, 1885-1978,", 1981 (Box-folder 5: 15)
    - "Third Country Migrant Workers and the Politics of European Integration: The Development of the European Community Social Policy, 1959-1977,", 1979 (Box-folder 5: 16)
    - Three Eritrean villages, typed outline, 1994 (Box-folder 5: 17)
    - Topics in Working Class-History, syllabus, 1979 (Box-folder 5: 18)
    - "Transformations in Eritrean National Consciousness, 1949-1962,", 1992 (Box-folder 5: 19)
    - "Transformations in Eritrean National Identity, 1949-1962,", 1992 (Box-folder 6: 1)
    - Turkish colonial period, 1980s (Box-folder 6: 2)
    - Union and number of workers, 1993 (Box-folder 6: 3)
    - Wad el-Hilewa, Sudan, 1980s (Box-folder 6: 4)
    - Woldeab Woldemariam (Welwel), 1983 (Box-folder 6: 5)
    - "Women Workers at 'Baratollo' Textile Factory,", 1994 (Box-folder 6: 6)
    - "Workers' Organization and the Struggle for Independence," part one, 1994 (Box-folder 6: 7)
- Subject File, 1868-1997 (Boxes 6-20)
  Contains African and Horn of Africa-related articles on labor, politics, economy, international relations, nationalities, refugees, rehabilitation, and development.
  - Africa, 1980-1994
    - "African Studies: A Dissident's View" [Gann, Lewis H., Academic Questions], 1989 (Box-folder 6: 8)
    - African Studies at Stanford and Berkeley, class and workshop schedule, 1980 (Box-folder 6: 9)
    - Replies to Lewis Gann in the forthcoming issue, 1989 (Box-folder 6: 10)
    - Archaeology
      - "Ancient Egypt and the Red Sea Trade: The Case for Obsidian in the Predynastic and Archaic Periods" [Zarins, Juris, Essays in Ancient Civilization Presented to Helene J. Kantor], undated (Box-folder 6: 11)
      - "The Origins of Agriculture" [Harlan, Jack], 1992 (Box-folder 6: 12)
    - Articles
      - "'Assassey Is Placed Under Arrest': Criminal Cases and the Problematic of Everyday Life in the Eastern Gold Coast in the 1840s" [Kea, Ray A.], 1990 (Box-folder 6: 13)
      - "Incarceration and Industrialization: Changes in Punishment in Late Nineteenth-Century, South Africa" [Worger, William H.], 1987 (Box-folder 6: 14)
    - International relations - U.S./Africa relationship ["Substantially New," Christopher addresses AAI], 1994 (Box-folder 6: 15)
    - Labor
      - The African Worker [Freund, Bill], 1988 (Box-folder 6: 16)
      - Dockworkers of Dar es Salaam [Iliffe, John, "The Creation of Group Consciousness Among the Dockworkers of Dar es Salaam, 1929-1950," in The Development of an African Working Class: Studies in Class Formation and Action], undated (Box-folder 6: 17)
      - "The 'Labor Aristocracy' in Africa: Introduction to a Debate" [Waterman, Peter, Development and Change], 1975 (Box-folder 6: 18)
      - The Labor Question in British and French Africa, 1935-1955 [Cooper, Frederick], 1986 (Box-folder 6: 19)
      - Migrant Laborers [Stichter, Sharon], 1985 (Box-folder 6: 20)
      - Rhodesian mine workers [van Onselen, Charles, "Worker Consciousness in Black Miners: Southern Rhodesia, 1900-1920," The Journal of African History], 1973 (Box-folder 6: 21)
      - West African railroad workers [Suret-Canale, J., "The French West African Railway Workers Strike, 1947-1948," in African Labor History], 1980 (Box-folder 6: 22)
  - Horn of Africa, 1868-1997
    - Accord - "L’accordo tra l’Italia e l’Etiopia,", 1957 (Box-folder 6: 23)
    - Agriculture
      - Early Warning and Food Information System for Eritrea (EWFIS), 1993 (Box-folder 7: 1)
        Includes preliminary crop assessment.
      - "Models for the Origins of Ethiopian Food Production,", 1984 (Box-folder 7: 2)
      - "The Antiquity of Cultivation and Herding in Ethiopia" [Phillipson, David W., in The Archaeology of Africa: Food, Metal and Towns], 1993 (Box-folder 7: 3)
    - Archaeology, Eritrea
      - "Archaeological and Environmental Observations in Rora Habab, Eritrea" [Jones, Scott, Azania: Archaeological Research in Africa], 1991 (Box-folder 7: 4)
      - Illustrations, 1990s (Box-folder 7: 5)
        Comprised of photographs and drawings.
      - "Preservation and Presentation of the Cultural Heritage" [Anfray, Francis], 1994 (Box-folder 7: 6)
      - "The British Museum Excavations at Adulis, 1868" [Munro-Hay, Stuart, The Antiquaries Journal], 1989 (Box-folder 7: 7)
      - "The Foreign Trade of the Aksumite Port of Adulis" [Munro-Hay, Stuart, Azania: Archaeological Research in Africa], 1982 (Box-folder 7: 8)
    - Archaeology, Ethiopia
      - "A Tyranny of Sources: The History of Aksum from Its Coinage" [Munro-Hay, Stuart, Northeast African Studies], 1981-1982 (Box-folder 7: 9)
      - "State Development and Urbanism in Northern Ethiopia" [Munro-Hay, Stuart, in The Archaeology of Africa: Food, Metals and Towns], 1994 (Box-folder 7: 10)
      - "The Christian Topography and the Kingdom of Axum," [Kirwan, L. P., The Geographical Journal], 1972 (Box-folder 7: 11)
    - Archaeology, Horn of Africa
      - Anfray’s bibliography, undated (Box-folder 7: 12)
      - "Late Quaternary Archaeological Research in the Horn of Africa" [Brandt,Steven and Fattovich, Rodolfo, in A History of African Archaeology], 1994 (Box-folder 7: 13)
    - Art
      - "The Profile of Writings on Ethiopian Medieval Christian Art" [Wolde, Seyoum], 1980 (Box-folder 7: 14)
      - "Putting African History on Film: A Retrospective on the Somali Film Project" [Geshekter, Charles L.], 1984 (Box-folder 7: 15)
    - Articles - Djibouti, undated (Box-folder 7: 16)
    - Articles, Eritrea
      - "Between Two Worlds" [Vigo, Anthony, Africa Today], 1965 (Box-folder 7: 17)
      - "Eclectic Notes on the Eritrean Liberation Movement" [Pliny the Middle-aged, Ethiopianist Notes], 1978 (Box-folder 7: 18)
      - Eritrea and the United Nations [Habte-Selassie, Bereket], 1989 (Box-folder 7: 19)
      - "Eritrean Customary Laws and the Constitution,", 1995 (Box-folder 7: 20)
      - "Eritrean Women" [ Spare Rib], 1979 (Box-folder 7: 21)
      - "Ferdinando Martini e l’amministrazione della colonia Eritrea,", undated (Box-folder 7: 22)
      - "Forging a Nation: The Eritrean Experience,", 1989 (Box-folder 7: 23)
      - "Freedom of Expression and Ethnic Discrimination in the Education System: Past and Present" [ Africa Watch], 1993 (Box-folder 7: 24)
      - "Hermeneutics of Literacy During Eritrea’s War of Independence" [Gottesman, Leslie, Eritrean Studies Review], 1996 (Box-folder 7: 25)
      - Introduction written by Woldeab Woldemariam, 1982 (Box-folder 7: 26)
      - "Labor and Liberty" [Killion, Tom], undated (Box-folder 7: 27)
      - "Nation Mourns Death of a Renowned Patriot: Woldeab Woldemariam,", 1995 (Box-folder 7: 28)
      - "No Story Down There,", 1984-1986 (Box-folder 7: 29)
      - "Notes on the Background to the Eritrean Problem: Early 1950-1960s" [Sishagne, Shumet], 1983 (Box-folder 7: 30)
      - "A Political and Legal Analysis of the Eritrean Question" [Berhane, Kahasai], undated (Box-folder 7: 31)
      - "Poverty, the Pen and the Sword,", 1993 (Box-folder 7: 32)
      - The Eritrean railroad systems, 1949-1996 (Box-folder 8: 1)
      - "Rebellion in Eritrea: Who Is Behind It; What Are Its Aims?" [Geremaw, Taye, New Middle East], 1971 (Box-folder 8: 2)
      - "Revolutionary Crisis and Revolutionary Vanguard: The Emergence of the Eritrean People’s Liberation Front" [Pool, David, Review of African Political Economy], 1980 (Box-folder 8: 3)
      - "Role of Asmara Students in the Eritrean Nationalist Movement, 1958-1968" [Ammar, Wolde-Yesus, Eritrean Studies Review], 1997 (Box-folder 8: 4)
      - "Significance of the Second and Unification Congress of the EPLF and ELF (CL)," [Selassie, Bereket Habte, Journal of Eritrean Studies], 1987 (Box-folder 8: 5)
      - "The Eritrean Revolution and Contemporary World Politics" [Petras, James], 1984 (Box-folder 8: 6)
      - "The Eritrean Struggle for Independence" [Heiden, Linda, Monthly Review], 1978 (Box-folder 8: 7)
      - "The Female Solider in Tigrinya Literature" [Kane, Thomas], 1994 (Box-folder 8: 8)
      - "The Genesis of the Differences in the Eritrean Secessionist Movement (1960-1970)," [Sishagne, Shumet], 1989 (Box-folder 8: 9)
      - "The International Dimension of the Eritrean Question" [Fessehatzion, Tekie, Horn of Africa], 1983 (Box-folder 8: 10)
      - "Woldeab Woldemariam: Reflections on a True Hero,", 1995 (Box-folder 8: 11)
    - Articles, Ethiopia
      - "An Archaeology of Work among the Malle of Southwest Ethiopia,", 1981 (Box-folder 8: 12)
      - "Ethiopia's High Level Manpower," analysis and projections conducted by Haile Selassie I. University, 1964 (Box-folder 8: 13)
      - "Ethiopia: From Monarchy to Military Socialism,", undated (Box-folder 8: 14)
      - "Frontier History of Ethiopia, Western Wellega: The Making of a Frontier Society" [Triulzi, Alessandro], 1991 (Box-folder 8: 15)
      - "Harar Town and Its Neighbours in the Nineteenth Century" [Caulk, R. A., Journal of African History], 1971 (Box-folder 8: 16)
      - "Hidden War in Ethiopia" [Kramer, Jack, Venture], 1969 (Box-folder 8: 17)
      - "In Ethiopia: Labor Unions Are Forced to Become Propaganda Arm for a Totalitarian Regime,", undated (Box-folder 8: 18)
      - "Italian Invasion of Ethiopia (1935): Indian Reactions,", 1991 (Box-folder 8: 19)
      - "L’Empire d’Éthiopie,", undated (Box-folder 8: 20)
      - "The Battle of Shire (February 1989): A Turning Point in the Protracted War in Ethiopia" [Melake, Tekeste], 1994 (Box-folder 8: 21)
      - "The Former Amirate of Harar Under Imperial Rule, 1887-1916,", 1981 (Box-folder 8: 22)
      - "Ethiopia: The Legal Setting,", 1969 (Box-folder 8: 23)
      - "The Occupation of Harar: January 1887" [Caulk, Richard A., Journal of Ethiopian Studies], 1971 (Box-folder 8: 24)
      - "Ethiopia: Myths and Consequences" [Tekle, Amare, The Horn Review], 1991 (Box-folder 8: 25)